for those of you who are familiar with
this modern stoicism movement you'll
know Massimo and he won't need any
introduction he's a professor of
philosophy at City College in New York
and apart from being known as a major
popularizer of modern stoicism he's also
a very outspoken advocate for scientific
literacy skepticism critical thinking he
actually has PhDs
plural in genetics evolutionary biology
and the philosophy of science and he's a
prolific blogger and that it has written
and edited over 10 books most recently
in 2019 very relevant to our conference
a handbook for new Stoics I'm gonna give
you about five minutes maybe or shortly
a little bit more than that of
introduction but in the meantime this is
a good time to take out your pen and
pencil and paper and all that sort of
stuff because this is gonna be an
interactive thing you will do the
exercises
now since is that this is not one of my
classes at City College I'm not gonna go
around and ask you personally to
volunteer the results of the exercise
but it would be nice actually
if after every exercise somebody wanted
to share how they did the exercise if
they if nobody does then fine I have my
backup option but but come on one of the
stoic values it's not not being shy
because what is going to happen people
are going to you know think badly of you
who cares that's not under your control
so about this book that I cover it with
my friend Greg Lopez the notion of the
book is that there is there is a lot of
there about stores in these days as you
might have noticed there's more and more
about stores now it's actually beginning
to look like you have to be careful and
selective about what you read because
there's a lot of books and many of them
are actually very very good books
there's a lot of introductory books to
stoicism but it's comparatively little
with the exception of some of the things
that Don axure is written that actually
is directly practical and you know if
you can look at this and say oh yeah now
I see what they mean by practice now
usually the practical part is kind of
left a little bit in the in limbo what
we did we greg was sort of the opposite
there's very little theory in the book
although there is a little bit because
it has to be there otherwise you don't
understand what's going on but it's most
about practices fifty-two exercises
ideally they're meant actually to be you
know worth a whole year of practice if
you want to although if you don't want
to commit that to that much in advance
we actually give an introduction or
shortcut and we said okay these are the
six fundamental exercise that we we
suggest you do so you commit to only six
weeks and then you see if you like it
good the bat that we make at the
beginning of the book is the same that
that arguably the Stoics had made since
Xena of sytem which is we all want to be
happy although the word happiness means
very different things to very different
people to many different people but
fundamentally you know nobody wants goes
around saying yes I really want to be
unhappy it's it's kind of an oxymoron
nobody asked why do you want to be a
happy happiness is the ultimate is the
ultimate good right it's now it's not an
instrumental and good it's not that you
have it you want it because you want to
do something else with it it's obviously
a good thing but most people bet on
externals for their happiness they want
to become rich they want to become
famous they want to become you know
esteemed by their colleagues they want
to be married they want to be with a
partner who loves them they want to have
all sorts of stuff and things and
people's opinions all of those are
external the storix bat is essentially
the opposite side
I'm sorry but all of that is actually a
lot of that is is up to luck
so all at the cosmic diet yes you can
influence it of course you can work on
your career you can work on your
relationship and so on but ultimately
you don't control it where is the one
thing you control the corn in the Stoics
well that's shaping your own character
that's really what you can do and so if
you bat your foot your happiness I'm
becoming the best person you can and
then let the chips fall where they may
that's that's the ideal and that's the
same idea of course of the book now we
start the book with a famous bit in the
discourse is three to three to one from
epictetus because it sets the whole tone
for the book and so I'm going to read it
to you it says there are three things in
which a man ought to exercise himself
who would be wise and good of course
these days we'll say there are three
things in which anyone ought to exercise
themselves who would be wise and good
the first concerns the desires and the
aversions that someone may not fail to
get what they desire and that they may
not fall into what they do not desire
keep this in mind for the first thing is
desires and aversions the second
concerns as a big leader the moments
toward an object and the movements from
an object and generally in doing what a
person ought to do that they may act
according to order to reason and not
carelessly so the second is the concern
with what you wanted to act or not to
act in the world and then the third
thing says epictetus concerns freedom
from deception and rashness in judgment
and generally it concerns your sense so
the third approach the third thing that
it's important is to make a few mistakes
as possible in arriving at judgments
about about things
these are famously after of the French
scholar peridot these are famously
referred to as the discipline of desire
and aversion the discipline of action
and the discipline of ascent basically
what they are if the discipline of
desire teaches us to reorient our
desires and aversions we really want
need to train ourselves to desire what
it's actually under our control and not
to be averse to things that are not in
their control the discipline of action
teaches us how to deal with other people
in the world which is you know
big deal given the were social species
and the discipline of a cent is the one
that teaches how to reason correctly
about our impressions and therefore
arrive at the best judgments and we can
so the the bad throughout the book the
book isn't is structured along the three
disciplines so there's a set of exercise
for the first discipline a second for
the second and a third
set for the third of discipline now as a
picture of himself said there is a
progression of these disciplines from a
pedagogical perspective you you start
with desires you continue with action
and you end up with a scent because the
scent is the more difficult one but
that's only pedagogical we go through
the same order in the book but in
reality in your life if you actually
have to make decisions obviously and
enact in the world you have to act at
the same time as you have to deal with
your desires at the same time as you
have to make judgments so all those
three actually go together which is why
today we're going to do one a minimum of
what exercise from each of the three
disciplines I have up to three so we're
depends on how much time we're gonna
have we're gonna go through one at least
and possibly two maybe three exercises
so let me start with the discipline of
desire and aversion for each exercise
well Greg and I did most to gain
inspiration directly from a stoic source
so each exercise actually starts out
with a quote from a stoic author not
only Epictetus so to crammed it in
actual stories I mean you know this is
stuff that the Stoics actually did but
then greg has a background in cognitive
behavioral therapy just like done and so
then we looked at the scientific enemas
my first academic career was as a
scientist so we looked at the actual
scientific evidence for what kind of
techniques that are that work well with
these kind of things actually have
evidence evidence based that things
actually work or don't work so the
actual exercise tends to take into
account what modern science has
suggested works or doesn't work so let's
start with the discipline a desire in a
version which remember is about
retraining your desires and your
versions you want to be desiring only
what is under your control and you want
to be averse only to not having what is
under your control
and the rest you have to accept you want
to train yourself to accept as it comes
the first exercise is on something about
that we already have heard quite a bit
about today we call it discover what's
really in your control and when it's not
so it's about the so called dichotomy or
control the famous are an obvious quote
there is Epictetus and karidian one of
all existing things some are in our
power and others are not in our power in
other power our thought impulse will to
get and will to avoid and in a word
everything which is our own doing things
not in our power include the body
property reputation office and in a word
everything which is not our own doing
you can see if you read the quote
carefully basically what he's saying is
what's under your control is your
internal decisions you know judgments
and values etc and what is not in your
control is pretty much everything else
so here's what the exercise consists on
so you
fog and this is where you come in to
them about to give you instructions to
know actually to do the exercise so if
organs and something that disturbed you
and happen to you recently so now you
know a year ago but just this fast
today's or last week or something like
that or maybe if something disturbed you
recently something that worries you and
it's likely to happen soon in the next
few days or the next next week so pick
one for now the exercise in the book of
course is done for any home for a whole
week so you have several occasions to do
it but pick one mentally focus on one
event either in the recent past that
upset you or in the near future that is
worrying you there is there is causing
you anxiety and then make a list of
which aspects of that thing that worries
you are actually under your control
and which ones are not ultimately under
your control you may be able to
influence them but they're not
ultimately under your control I'll give
you two minutes go
I'll wait okay anybody wants to
volunteer without divulging personal
details you know don't say oh I got mad
at my aunt whatever that it doesn't
matter who that was but someone yeah
let me repeat it slowly when you're
doing because for the camera so you have
a work meeting tomorrow morning yeah
with someone that you will able
difficult I'm sure we all had that kind
of experience yep
[Music]
okay so under your control are you
prepare for for the meeting and how
you're you're thinking ahead of the
meeting meaning that you want to
convince yourself that you could you
need to assume the other person is
actually in good faith and what's the
third one thing the FIR and how you
treated during the during the meeting
what is on not in your control what you
will say her emotional reactions her
opinions of you the outcome of the
meeting or actual decisions right
exactly so this is the way work it works
so what's the point of this kind of
exercise if you do it regularly because
you know it's easy to so Greg and I have
this dispute I think the stories ism is
one part theory in nine part practice he
thinks that it's three part theory and
seven part practice and the joke is that
typically between the two of us is the
one that's more interested in the
practice and I mean more interested in
the theory but whatever the proportion
is we both agreed that it that the
practice is more than 50% right so the
notion is that in a lot of stoic Theory
is easy to understand a lot of it is
easy to misunderstand I mean like right
constantly about even professional
philosophers misunderstanding stories
but it's not just that you don't just
need to understand you need to actually
use it right so if you do this kind of
thing every time that you that you
encounter a situation like that then the
idea is and that's the goal of the
exercise to internalize the dichotomy or
control right to shift from worry about
outcomes to the kinds of stuff that's
actually under your control so you are
no longer averse to the outcome because
you don't control it you're only averse
to bad preparation on your part because
that's the part you control right all
right so the second exercise is the
discipline from from the discipline of
action the discipline of action member
has to deal with how to deal with other
people in in in the Cosmopolis and we
live in a society and so we always have
to act in certain ways or not act in
other words
from the book this is exercise 18 for
those of you who odd will actually have
the book and we got to keep your peace
of mind in mind the pertinent quote is
again from the picked eaters
this time from enchiridion four and this
is actually one of my favorite quotes
from epic leaders he says when you're
about to take something in hand remind
yourself what manner of thing it is if
you're going to bathe put before your
mind what happens in the bath water
pouring over some others being jostled
some reveling others stealing and you
will set to work more securely if you
say to yourself at once I want to bathe
and I want to keep my will in our money
with nature and in so it's so in each
thing you do for in this way if anything
turns up to hinder you in your bathing
you will be ready to say I did not want
only to bathe but to keep my will in our
money with nature and I shall not so
keep it if I go to pieces every time
someone splash in some water with me
right so so this is about preparing
yourself for situations that may be more
stressful than you might think or that
you may you want to enjoy and then at
the same time something's going to
possibly happen is gonna ruin that
experience by keeping harmony with
nature in modern parlance we're
epictetus will say is keeping harmony
with the rest of the community and with
yourself right so don't get upset so
it's the subside no no we react to
situations I get you know angry and
start yelling at people and that's our
stuff so there are three steps to this
exercise step 1 visualize a task you are
likely to encounter today or in the near
future that you sometimes find
frustrating mentally realize I want to
do this activity but also want to keep
my cool by accepting what happens or
something like that whatever works for
you and then finally imagine yourself
behaving calmly in the situation so this
is a kind of a visualization exercise so
I'll give you another two minutes close
your eyes and imagine something that
normally is pleasurable for you but it
may go badly it may be ruined by
something and and visualize how you're
going to react tell yours
I want to do two things here the
objective is to do the D activity but
also to keep harmony with nature and
then visualize how the thing is going to
go and you keeping your calm so again a
little less than two minutes just close
your eyes it actually helps if you focus
close your eyes and think about a
particular situation not just in general
a very particular situation something
you normally enjoy but it may be ruined
by other people so anyone wants to share
a particular situation that they
normally enjoy but it may get frustrated
somebody's being volunteered that's
right somebody's volunteers this week
that's something you can't control
what's the what's the situation at any
conference today in Taunton Toronto okay
you normally find pleasurable thing in
the subway that's good for you I live in
New York so I you know but to me that
that thought is alien but yes go ahead
right so the whole system slow down
because somebody else is acting like you
would say a jerk okay
correct so your your your possible
options are either you say well this is
completely under my control it's on I
can can actually go down the system and
somehow solve the situation so I can
just you know pull out a book and read
while I'm waiting and if I'm gonna be
late I'm gonna be late or you can get
upset and make your situation even worse
because you were already upset in the
beginning to the beginning that's right
so my own favorite example of this kind
of exercise is going to the movies and
you know lights go down and the movie
starts and is jerk just two words before
me just pulled out the phone because he
absolutely has to
Facebook or messages or whatever the
hell it is that they people check these
days and so then used to upset me a lot
because I can't believe how somebody
would do that like how do you not
understand that this is a problem for
everybody else behind you but then I
started saying well I have two
objectives when I go to the movies right
one is to enjoy the movie and the other
one is not to get upset now to get you
know out of harmony with nature and
certainly I'm not gonna enjoy the movie
if I get upset so if there is that
person you know if the person is in
earshot from me I might politely go
there and say hey would you mind
sometimes that works sometimes it
doesn't work and if it doesn't work you
still have options you can go back to
your seat and try to enjoy the movie or
you can go home as for a refund from the
movie theater and then go home and watch
Netflix right so you have options very
card train yeah exactly if everybody
else gets agitated and you just join
into the agitation they think I'm again
make it any better right very good
okay so there was what two down the
third exercise is the first one from the
discipline of ascent so the discipline
of ascent is supposed to help us arrive
at better judgments about situations
right so cool so using essentially it's
a pair though connects the discipline of
ascent to the study of stoic logic
because it's it's about learning how to
think better about certain situations so
bear with me because here that the quote
it's a little long but it's worth it
worth it
it's from Seneca from the letters to
Lucilius and particularly from letter 71
sections 30 33 the wise person indeed
overcomes fortune by its virtue but many
who profess wisdom are sometimes
frightened by the most unsubstantial
trait flat
and at this stage it is a mistake on our
part to make the same demands upon the
wise person and upon the learner I still
exhort myself to do which I recommend
that which I recommend but my
exhortations are not yet followed so
he's saying he's basically practice
practice in humility sighs now I know
what to do I still fail to do it at
least some of the times and even if
these were the case I should not have
these principles so ready for practice
or so well trained that they will rush
to my assistance in every crisis this
says you know even if I try I don't
always remember immediately what I
should do what I what I should bring up
to my mind to deal with the situation
just as wool takes up certain colors at
once while there are others which will
not absorb unless it is soaked and
steeped in them many times
so other systems of doctrine there is
other philosophies can be immediately
applied by men's minds after once being
accepted but this system of which I
speak stoicism unless it has gone deep
and has sunk in for a long time and is
not merely colored but thoroughly
permeated the soul does not fulfill any
of its promises
so sanic I says you gotta be thinking
about this stuff carefully it has to
reshape your mind it has to reshape the
way you think about stuff otherwise
isn't gonna work so how does the actual
exercise going to work take a couple of
minutes and make a shortlist of four or
five handy stoic precepts in your own
words so things that you think short
phrases that you think reflect stoic
thinking or stoic advice on how to deal
with situations that are going to be
useful but write them in your own in
your own way your own phrasing let's
keep a minute and a half or something
like that all right anybody wants to
volunteer yeah
this too shall pass this too shall pass
but if it was a gift thinking about
something by parently negative in my
turn and go positive one yoga bear
whatever you're you go there you are
sorry what's that
just keep swimming that's right great
back there don't take it personally
yep that's one change is inevitable
that's actually one of my favorite yes
and look at nature if you don't believe
it oh nice
are you demonic my life need not be
pleasant that's right every cloud has a
silver lining is very similar to the two
handles idea you don't you look at it
differently it may have may actually
help
that's my favorites but Odysseus says
those those lines in the in Inferno by
Dante yes 14 on foster baby become a
broody mapper seguir able to take on a
chance' that's that that's in Italian
yes good thank you
13th century Italian yeah so some of my
favorites are you know obviously some
things are up to me other things are not
up to me everything changes
it seems so to him or her so it's that's
her opinion and it's probably considered
opinion I just happen to disagree I wish
to keep harmony with nature as we said
earlier and then also what done referred
earlier as the reserve clause I will do
this fit permitting or for Fortuna
allowing or something like that rights
like meaning that I always am always
conscious that I'm committing to things
but other stuff can get in the way and I
might not be able it may be beyond my my
own mean
to actually deal with with the situation
right so I think we're getting close to
the end of time not the real handle
times then there are my time so let me
let me conclude with so there's lot more
exercises of course along along these
lines in the book based basically that
gives you a flavor at least of what it
means to do exercises as a stoic now
some of the exercises in the book are
actually physical which for obvious
reasons we didn't do here like taking a
cold shower
that would have been logistically
difficult for you to do right here in
the in the middle of the tank right or
fasting for a day or two something that
were abstaining from alcohol for an
inning or two or something like that now
why the hell would anybody want to do
that those kind of sort of self all most
self-flagellating exercise these are
mild exercises in self-denial these are
not you're not supposed to be you know
starving yourself near death or anything
like that or you're not supposed to go
out in the cold naked in the middle of
the January winter as Chuck was saying
this morning in Toronto that's not the
idea the notion there however is
interesting so if you do those kinds of
exercises that sort of you deny yourself
something one of my favorite actually is
the walk through the mall I actually go
to a mall large mall where there's a lot
of shopping of shops and then I go very
deliberately throughout every shop
looking at everything and then walk out
the other side without having bought
anything and I repeat myself what
Socrates allegedly said which was I
didn't know there were so many things I
didn't need right so why would you want
to do that sort of stuff because the
idea is is this this several reasons the
monies remind yourself that a lot of
stuff that you think you absolutely need
in order to have a good life or to
Levitz you could actually do without if
forced to if in a pinch or if you know
the situation changes you could actually
do without a lot of stuff you can you
are strong enough to actually go through
a little bit of you know you're
resilient
in a resilient enough to actually go
through a little bit of discomfort but
the other side is kind of the opposite
it's like a exercising in thankfulness
as Seneca says in one of the letters to
Lucy races you know I went a couple of
days fasting you wouldn't believe how
good that the stale bread and soup taste
it when when I got back home and I
actually hate my first dinner after
after two days right so in a sense it's
an exercise in in fact fulness modern
psychologists often refer to the so
called atonic treadmill this notion and
we get used to new things the trail of a
new iphone or a new car or a new
whatever it's great for a few days or a
for a few hours and then you know a
following week so yeah I got my phone do
without your phone for a day and then
you'll see how you appreciate the fact
that you have essentially a computer
with incredible power in your pockets
all the time that you can actually use
for good stuff and not just for
bothering somebody at the movies by
checking your messages thank you very
much